Arun Baby | Speech Researcher

www.arunbaby.com • www.linkedin.com/in/arunbaby0

About

I am passionate about research, technologies, have a broad engineering background, and love developing myself, the people around me, and leading teams.

Professional Interests: Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Conversational AI, Speech Synthesis, Automatic Speech Recognition, Text to Speech Systems, Speech tech for Indian Languages, Data Science.

Professional Experience - 10+ years

Samsung Research(SRI-B) - Staff Engineer(Senior Chief Engineer).....

On-Device ASR(Acqui-hired from Zapr Media Labs)

Speech Research Team(ASR)

Apr 2022 - present Samsung Research

- ASR model compression.
- On-device model optimisations.
- Streaming and hybrid ASR models.
- Environment: Tensorflow, Python, Bash.



Zapr Media Labs(acquired by Samsung) - Research Scientist(Speech).....

Conversational AI Jan 2020 - Apr 2022

Speech Research Team

Zapr Media Labs

- VoiceBots Speech based bot for automatic customer assistance.
- Achieved around 80% call success for feedback and ratings voicebots with preliminary deployments.
- VoiceAnalytics Customer care data analytics for better user engagement.
- Achieved 10-30% relative WER improvements compared to commercial ASR systems.
- Speech research training and deployment framework architect.
- Created a scalable kubeflow framework for parallel training/inference for 100s of models.
- Context-based ASR systems for Indian Languages: 50% NER improvement.
- Controllable expressive text-to-speech: speed and pitch controllablity.
- o Bilingual models for Indian Languages.
- Indian English optimizations for TTS and ASR models.
- Automated Phonetic rules for Indian English models.
- A 20% relative improvement in MOS scores for Indian English and Hindi TTS models.
- NLP for grapheme to phonemes.
- 3 speech research article submissions in international conferences.
- 1 accepted patent.
- Mentored 2 juniors.
- Environment: ESPnet, Kaldi, PyTorch, ParallelWaveGAN, Huggingface, VOSK, IndicNLP,
- FastAPI, docker, kubeflow, kubernets, gRPC.
- AWS, GCP.

Cisco Systems - Software Engineer II.....

Data Center debug analytics for routing products

Enterprise Networking

Aug 2018 - Jan 2020

Cisco Systems

zapr

- Lossless logging, improvements in debuggability, and analytics for debugging.
- Up to 80% memory footprint reduction for debuger logs.
- Code optimisations for 10% faster code execution.
- o IPv4, IPv6 code maintenance.
- Environment: C, Linux, Python.



Development of text-to-speech synthesis systems for Indian languages (Research)

MeitY, Govt. of India

IIT Madras

- Development of a language independent parser across 13 Indian languages.
- **Segmentation of phonemes** using signal processing cues and machine learning (deep learning) techniques.
- **Development of voice models** for 13 Indian languages using HTS (a parametric speech synthesis toolkit) and Merlin (a neural network based speech synthesis toolkit).
- Integration of the unified parser to the IndicTTS application in **Android platform**.
- Knowledge transfer to Samsung Research Institute Noida, IndusOS and ShinanoKenshi.
- Lead and managed IITM TTS team along with collaborating with 11 organisations across the country.
- o Environment: C, Python, Perl, Shell, HTK, Kaldi, HTS, Merlin (TTS) and Android.

HCL Technologies - Software Engineer.....

Web and Mobile Applications - Development and Maintenance KnowledgePoint360 Group

Jan 2013 - Jul 2014 HCL Technologies

KnowledgePoint360 Group LLC provides multi-channel health-care communication and advisory services for pharmaceutical industries, industries related to biotechnology and health-care professionals.

- Lead the PoC development of web based app for improving the efficiency of physicians in USA.
- Lead major back-end development/maintenance of the product development for a team of 4.
- Development of a multi-platform and cross browser web application from scratch for managing physicians and speakers (medical representatives).
- Development of an interface to verify speaker's and physician's data by Verisys with automatic syncing to the web application.

HCL

- **Maintenance** of core applications, new portal, mobile applications and services across different projects.
- Performance optimization of front-end and back-end services.
- Management of project kick-off activities.
- Environment: Visual Studio, C#, ASP.net, MVC, HTML5, JavaScript, jQuery, CSS and SQL Server.

Database Query Optimization for Statistical Data

Jun 2012 - Dec 2012

Thomson Reuters

HCL Technologies

Thomson Financial, a popular financial management company, handles stock market data.

- Optimization of SQL jobs to perform statistical data analysis.
- o Development of a multiple job scheduler to improve the efficiency of the system.
- HCL

Environment: SQL Server and SSIS.

Delphi to .Net Migration

Oct 2011 - Jun 2012

Triple Point Technology

HCL Technologies

The company provides real-time, innovative solutions to the complex issues that arise in the management of the commodity supply chain.

- Development of a PoC application for multi-market commodity and enterprise risk management.
- Environment: .NET framework 3.5, C#, WPF and XML.

Education

M.S. (By Research)

2015 - 2018

Computer Science and Engineering

Indian Institute of Technology Madras

- Supervisor: Prof. Hema A Murthy
- Thesis: A Unified Approach to Building Speech Synthesis Systems in Indian Languages
- o CGPA: 7.8/10
- Key courses: Pattern Recognition, Kernel Methods for Pattern Analysis, Speech Technology, Linear Algebra and Random Processes, Advanced Data Structures and Algorithms





o Thesis: Parallel C - A Serial to Parallel C Code Converter

• Percentage: 75/100



Publications: Google Scholar link

- Arun Baby, Pranav Jawale, Saranya Vinnaitherthan, Sumukh Badam, Nagaraj Adiga, Sharath Adavanne Non-native English lexicon creation for bilingual speech synthesis, Speech Synthesis Workshop(SSW), August 2021.
- Arun Baby, Jeena J Prakash, Aswin Shanmugam S and Hema A Murthy, Significance of Spectral Cues in Automatic Speech Segmentation for Indian Language Speech Synthesizers, Speech Communication, Oct 2020.
- Arun Baby, Saranya Vinnaitherthan, Nagaraj Adiga, Pranav Jawale, Sumukh Badam, Sharath Adavanne, Srikanth Konjeti An ASR Guided Speech Intelligibility Measure for TTS Model Selection, arXiv pre-print, May 2020.
- Arun Baby, A Unified Approach to Building Speech Synthesis Systems in Indian Languages, MS Thesis, IIT Madras, 2019.
- Anju Leela Thomas, Anusha Prakash, Arun Baby, and Hema A Murthy, Code-switching in Indic Speech Synthesisers, INTERSPEECH 2018, 1948-1952, Hyderabad, India.
- Arun Baby, Karthik Pandia DS and Hema A Murthy, Signal Processing Cues to Improve Automatic Speech Recognition for Low Resource Indian Languages, SLTU 2018, 25-29, Gurugram, India.
- Arun Baby, Jeena Prakash, Rupak Vignesh and Hema A Murthy, Deep Learning Techniques in Tandem with Signal Processing Cues for Phonetic Segmentation for Text to Speech Synthesis in Indian Languages, INTERSPEECH 2017, 3817-3821, Stockholm, Sweden.
- Atish Ghone, Rachana Nerpagar, Pranaw Kumar, Arun Baby, Aswin Shanmugam, Sasikumar Mukundan and Hema A Murthy, TBT (Toolkit to Build TTS): A High Performance Framework to build Multiple Language HTS Voice, INTERSPEECH 2017 (Show and Tell), 3427-3428, Stockholm, Sweden.
- Arun Baby, Anju Thomas, Jeena Prakash, Anusha Prakash and Hema A Murthy, **Speech Synthesis in Indian Languages and Future Perspectives**, Global Conference on Cyberspace (GCCS), November 2017.
- Arun Baby, Jeena Prakash and Hema A Murthy, A Hybrid Approach to Neural Networks based Speech Segmentation, Frontiers of Research in Speech and Music (FRSM), December 2017.
- Arun Baby, Nishanthi N L, Anju Leela Thomas, and Hema A Murthy, A Unified Parser for Developing Indian Language Text to Speech Synthesizers, International Conference on Text, Speech, and Dialogue, pp. 514-521, Brno, Czech Republic, September 2016.
- Arun Baby, Anju Leela Thomas, Nishanthi N L, and TTS Consortium, Resources for Indian Languages, CBBLR Workshop, International Conference on Text, Speech, and Dialogue, pp. 37–43, Brno, Czech Republic, September 2016.
- Anusha Prakash, Arun Baby, Aswin Shanmugam S, Jeena J Prakash, Nishanthi N L, Raghava Krishnan K, Rupak Vignesh Swaminathan and Hema A Murthy, Blizzard Challenge 2015: Submission by DONLab, IIT Madras, Blizzard Challenge, Berlin, Germany, September 2015.

Academic Projects

Signal Processing and Machine Learning Projects

July 2015 - May 2016

Pattern Recognition, Kernel Methods for Pattern Analysis, Speech Technology

IIT Madras

- Classification techniques: Bayes classifier, GMM, HMM, DNN, CNN and SVM.
- Clustering techniques: k-means and Support Vector Clustering.
- Regression techniques: simple linear regression, polynomial regression and Support Vector Regression.
- Learning methods: supervised, semi-supervised and unsupervised.
- Applications: Speaker Recognition using signal processing cues and acoustic modeling.
- Environment: Matlab, C++, Perl, Shell and Torch.

Course Work

Key Courses

Core and electives

January 2015 - May 2016

IIT Madras

- Pattern Recognition
- Kernel Methods for Pattern Analysis
- Speech Technology

- Data Structures and Algorithms
- Linear Algebra and Random Processes

Skills and Tools

- o Languages C, C++, C#, Perl, Shell and Python
- Operating Systems Linux and Windows
- o Applications and Tools Visual Studio, HTK, Festival, Kaldi, Merlin (TTS), ESPnet MATLAB and Pytorch
- Database MYSQL and SQL Server
- Web development HTML5, PHP, XML, CSS, JavaScript, jQuery and Flask

Positions of Responsibility

- Coordinator for speech research publishing at Zapr Media Labs.
- Point of Contact for lossless logging for Netstack team.
- Point of Contact for industrial collaboration for TTS resources at IIT Madras.
- Technology Expert/Point of Contact for ASP.NET MVC 4 and jQuery across the projects at HCL Technologies.
- Point of Contact of speaker verification project (Web and Mobile Application Development and Maintenance, KnowledgePoint360 Group, HCL Technologies).

Co - Curricular Activities

- Member of International Speech Communication Association (ISCA).
- Reviewer for **ICON** 2018, 2019.
- Presented 2 papers in INTERSPEECH 2017.
- Presented 2 papers in TSD 2016.
- Attended Winter School on Speech and Audio Processing (WiSSAP), 2016.
- Finalist in **Bootcamp 17** a startup bootcamp event at IIT Madras.
- Participated in Microsoft **code.fun.do** in 2016 and 2017.
- Won awards for various Inter-school and college maths quizzes.
- Won awards for **coding and debugging** competitions at various **technical fests**.

Extra - Curricular Activities

- Participated in the 8^{th} edition of Terry Fox Run Chennai 2016.
- Member of Disaster Management Team, IIT Madras 2016-17.
- Member of IIT Madras Volleyball team.
- Member of Volleyball, Table Tennis, Tennis, Basketball, Badminton and Squash Hostel teams at IIT Madras.
- **Hapkido** practitioner since 2016 (3^{rd} Kup).